Ludwig. He loved women. He loved men. He lived as controversially as he ruled.
But he did not care what the world thought. He was the world.
Ludwig is a drama, history film directed by Luchino Visconti.
Historical evocation of Ludwig, king of Bavaria, from his crowning
in 1864 until his death in 1886, as a romantic hero.
Fan of Richard Wagner, betrayed by him, in love with his cousin Elisabeth of Austria, abandoned by
her, tormented by his homosexuality, he will little by little slip towards madness.
Ludwig, played by Helmut Berger.
Elisabeth of Austria, played by Romy Schneider.
Richard Wagner, played by Trevor Howard.
Cosima von Bülow, played by Silvana Mangano.
Father Hoffmann, played by Gert Fröbe.
Dürckheim, played by Helmut Griem.
Ludwig (German: Ludwig II.) is a 1973 epic biographical drama
film co-written and directed by Luchino Visconti.
The film stars Helmut Berger as King Ludwig II of Bavaria and Romy Schneider as Empress Elisabeth of
Austria, along with Trevor Howard, Silvana Mangano, Helmut Griem, and Gert Fröbe.
It is the third and final part of Visconti's "German Trilogy",
following The Damned (1969) and Death in Venice (1971).
An international co-production by Italian producer Ugo Santalucia and West German producer Dieter Giessler, Ludwig was one of the most expensive European films at the time, and
was a moderate success in its home territories, but was more lukewarmly received in the United States, where a heavily truncated 177-minute version was released.
It was filmed in Munich and surrounding parts of
Bavaria, and at Cinecittà Studios.
Ludwig won two David di Donatello Awards, for Best Film and Best Director, and
was nominated for an Academy Award for Best Costume Design.
Berger and Schneider both received German Film Award nominations for their acting, and
Berger won a "Special David di Donatello" for his portrayal of the King.
The film explores themes of friendship, bavaria, germany,
biography, herrenchiemsee, male homosexuality.
The tone is emotional.